<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Writings on Sven Hofstede</title><link>https://svenhofstede.com/writings/</link><description>Recent content in Writings on Sven Hofstede</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 26 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://svenhofstede.com/writings/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Programming side projects for this year</title><link>https://svenhofstede.com/writings/projects-for-this-year/</link><pubDate>Sun, 26 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://svenhofstede.com/writings/projects-for-this-year/</guid><description>These are my intended side-project goals for this year. Obviously some of them will be very limited in scope and won&amp;rsquo;t be anything special. It&amp;rsquo;s all about getting a feel for how this stuff works instead of building production ready products. I also plan to document the progress for each of these projects by livestreaming on Youtube. Two additional goals that I&amp;rsquo;m setting is to use TDD and Functional programming in atleast one of the projects.</description></item><item><title>What I’m struggling with as a self-learner</title><link>https://svenhofstede.com/writings/self-learn-struggles/</link><pubDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://svenhofstede.com/writings/self-learn-struggles/</guid><description>Pretty soon I will be starting a new job where I will be working as a Java developer. I have some professional experience writing Scala code (Spark) but this was in a different context. Moving data around is very different to application development. I&amp;rsquo;m therefore spending a couple hours each week brushing up on my programming skills and I thought it would be interesting to document the struggles I&amp;rsquo;m currently facing.</description></item><item><title>My News Diet</title><link>https://svenhofstede.com/writings/the-news-diet/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://svenhofstede.com/writings/the-news-diet/</guid><description>I actively try to avoid any type of news/media. I have de-activated my Facebook account. I don&amp;rsquo;t read newspapers or magazines.
Total connectivity My friend was in New Zealand a couple of months back. This is quite literally the other side of the world to where I live. While he was there an severe earthquake struck the island. According to him, he was reading about the earthquake on belgian news sites 10 minutes after it happened.</description></item><item><title>Things I should learn as a new programmer</title><link>https://svenhofstede.com/writings/things-i-should-learn/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://svenhofstede.com/writings/things-i-should-learn/</guid><description>Algorithms &amp;amp; Data Structures There are literally limitless ways to solve any given problem. A good programmer will know the right tool for the job by using existing Algorithms and Data Structures.
I think it&amp;rsquo;s also a good idea to have the basic intuition of how well known algorithms work. For example, know how the various sorting algorithms are implemented. This will highlight good algorithn design.
I also plan to eventually finish the Algorithms course on Coursera starting here.</description></item><item><title>What Clean Code taught me</title><link>https://svenhofstede.com/writings/clean-code-summary/</link><pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://svenhofstede.com/writings/clean-code-summary/</guid><description>This blog post is work-in-progress while working myself through the book. It will loosely follow the structure of the book.
I&amp;rsquo;m currently working on reading through Clean Code by Robert C. Martin. It was clear from the start that the book is full of incredible content and it&amp;rsquo;s well worth the time to study it properly. I&amp;rsquo;m trying to capture the key take-aways I have come across. There is much more to the book then what I&amp;rsquo;m highlighting here but these are things that were somewhat new to me and stuck in my mind as being worth remembering.</description></item><item><title>My Reading List</title><link>https://svenhofstede.com/writings/book-list/</link><pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://svenhofstede.com/writings/book-list/</guid><description>My ever-evolving reading list for the coming weeks, months, years :)
You can click on the [★★★★★]({% post_url 2016-12-02-book-list %}) icons to link to a review I wrote.
Programming Clean Code - Robert C. Martin [★★★★★]({% post_url 2016-12-12-clean-code-summary %}) Code Complete - Steve McConnell Head First Design Patterns - Eric Freeman, Elisabeth Robson, Bert Bates, Kathy Sierra Structure and Interpretation of Computer Programs - Harold Abelson, Gerald Jay Sussman, Julie Sussman Code: The Hidden Language of Computer Hardware and Software - Charles Petzold Agile Software Development Principles - Robert C.</description></item><item><title>Homer's face.. with a Random Forest!</title><link>https://svenhofstede.com/writings/homers-face-random-forest/</link><pubDate>Sat, 19 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://svenhofstede.com/writings/homers-face-random-forest/</guid><description>Classifying Simpsons characters in images Dataset: Many thanks to jbencina for making this dataset available. The dataset is available on github here:
Collection of 30,693 frames from 65 Simspsons episodes from seasons 3, 4, and 5. Each image is 160x120 pixels.
One collection (faces-clean-color) contains isolated frames of Homer (n=1,041), Marge (n=444), Lisa (n=358), and Bart (n=645) totalling (n=2,488). These files are labled as {instance_number}_{character_name}.jpg.
The second collection (unsorted-color) contains 28,205 unsorted frames which can contain backgrounds, characters, text, etc.</description></item><item><title>Create radar chart in Tableau</title><link>https://svenhofstede.com/writings/radar-chart-tableau/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://svenhofstede.com/writings/radar-chart-tableau/</guid><description>Radar charts Radar charts is a two dimensional graph that allows for visualizing numerous amount of measures. Normally the number of measures would be at least 4 to give the radar charts it&amp;rsquo;s distinct shape. Many more measures can be displayed, each adding a new &amp;lsquo;leg&amp;rsquo; to graph. The radar chart is sometimes also referred to as a Spider chart.
The larger the value, the further the data point is plotted towards the outside of the graph.</description></item><item><title>Why start blogging</title><link>https://svenhofstede.com/writings/why-start-blogging/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://svenhofstede.com/writings/why-start-blogging/</guid><description>The reason There are a couple of reason why I think it&amp;rsquo;s a great idea to start a blog, especially as an IT professional.
Showcase what you can do The main reason I&amp;rsquo;m starting to blog is because I think it&amp;rsquo;s a great way to show what you&amp;rsquo;re good at. You can really showcase your expertise by writing in-depth articles on your subject matter. It&amp;rsquo;s freely available 24/7 for anyone interested and it gets your name or brand out there.</description></item><item><title>Predicting titanic survivors</title><link>https://svenhofstede.com/writings/predicting-titanic-survivors/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://svenhofstede.com/writings/predicting-titanic-survivors/</guid><description>Predicting Titanic Survivors.. again Yes.. I also decided to give the Titanic survival prediction a go. It&amp;rsquo;s probably the go-to starting point for people wanting to learn Machine Learning. Apart from some missing values the dataset itself is pretty clean, the label we are trying to predict &amp;lsquo;makes sense&amp;rsquo;. You can easily reason about what we are going for. If you&amp;rsquo;ve watched the movie you will also have a good idea about what features might be useful ( Woman and children first!</description></item><item><title>Big O Notation</title><link>https://svenhofstede.com/writings/big-o-notation/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://svenhofstede.com/writings/big-o-notation/</guid><description>Big-O notation illustrates how a function responds to various inputs. Simply put: How fast will my function run if I change the input from 10 elements to 1000000 elements. Big-O is all about the approximate worst-case performance of doing something. The upper bound is the mathematic limit of the worst output.
log of 50 = x
10^x = 50
To the power of what do I need to raise 10 to end up with 50.</description></item><item><title>Josh Wills - The Life of a Data Scientist</title><link>https://svenhofstede.com/writings/tech-talk-josh-wills/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://svenhofstede.com/writings/tech-talk-josh-wills/</guid><description>Traits of Data scientist Being relentless in a lazy way Most of your model assumptions are incorrect. He mentions 2/3 of his ideas failed. Being lazy means you DO move on to the next idea and don&amp;rsquo;t stick to it.
Humility Being at best competent as a statician and scientist. You know enough to talk to expert but you&amp;rsquo;re not an expert but this allows you to learn.
Math vs.</description></item><item><title>What I think of Tableau</title><link>https://svenhofstede.com/writings/two-years-of-using-tableau-what-do-i-think/</link><pubDate>Sat, 20 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://svenhofstede.com/writings/two-years-of-using-tableau-what-do-i-think/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been working with Tableau professionally for the past two years. I create ready-to-use dashboard for end-users who typically consume them via the Tableau Server portal. I feel however that this is not the best use for Tableau and I&amp;rsquo;ll go into details why further on. Let&amp;rsquo;s start with some of the highlights.
+ As easy as Excel Tableau is great. I would advise anyone to go check it out if you are looking for an easy-to-learn, professional package for data exploration/analysis.</description></item><item><title>Creating a home gym</title><link>https://svenhofstede.com/writings/creating-a-home-gym/</link><pubDate>Fri, 09 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://svenhofstede.com/writings/creating-a-home-gym/</guid><description>The Why I finally decided to invest in my own homegym. I&amp;rsquo;ve been going to a commercial gym for the past two years but lately have been slacking. I prefer to train in the morning or in the evenings. Unfortunately my gym opens at 8AM and in the evenings it&amp;rsquo;s very busy. Like queue-up-for-every-rack/bench busy. Being able to workout whenever I want to seemed pretty convenient so I sat down, did some calculations and came to the conclusion that the costs of buying everything for my home gym won&amp;rsquo;t be so bad.</description></item><item><title>Airbnb in New York</title><link>https://svenhofstede.com/writings/airbnb/</link><pubDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://svenhofstede.com/writings/airbnb/</guid><description>I find Airbnb itself to be an interesting concept. Renting out any left over space you might have in your home seems like a great way of earning some extra cash while at the same time meeting new people.
Initial datasets Airbnb provides datasets containing all the airbnb listings a number of large cities through insideairbnb. I thought it would be cool to have a look at some of this data.</description></item></channel></rss>